Preliminary Guide to the Harold Jantz Papers, 1500-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Harold Jantz papers 1500-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jantz, Harold Stein
60288 Items
Noted professor of German literature and collector of German baroque literature.
Professional correspondence, note cards, research and teaching files, essays, offprints and reprints of articles by Jantz and scholars associated with him, and other printed material. Notable items are manuscripts about Johann Wolfgang von Goethe and his FAUST, and manuscripts related to Francis Daniel Pastorius's Bee-Hive. Accession (2008-0159) consists largely of Jantz's correspondence and letters, 1978-1985. Also included are exam blue books, some miscellaneous printed material, and a scrapbook of chromolithographs dating from the Victorian period. The blue books contain writings by Jantz, some relating to Francis Pastorius, and are arranged numerically.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Harold Jantz Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift, 1990-2008.
Biographical Note
Harold Jantz was a Professor of German literature at Northwestern, Johns Hopkins, and Duke Universities, and a collector of German baroque literature and German Americana.
Collection Overview
Professional correspondence, note cards, research and teaching files, essays, offprints and reprints of articles by Jantz and scholars associated with him, and other printed material. Notable items are manuscripts about Johann Wolfgang von Goethe and his FAUST, and manuscripts related to Francis Daniel Pastorius's Bee-Hive. Accession (2008-0159) consists largely of Jantz's correspondence and letters, 1978-1985. Also included are exam blue books, some miscellaneous printed material, and a scrapbook of chromolithographs dating from the Victorian period. The blue books contain writings by Jantz, some relating to Francis Pastorius, and are arranged numerically.
Collection Arrangement
This collection has not been processed and therefore no arrangement has been completed at this time.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Jantz, Harold
Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832
Goethe, Johann Wolfgang von, 1749-1832. Faust
German literature -- History and criticism
Pastorius, Francis Daniel, 1651-1719
Chromolithographs
Scrapbooks
Advertisements
Correspondence
Related Material
The Harold Jantz collection of early manuscripts, music manuscripts, and autograph albums, 1477-1905 is also housed at Duke University. The collection consists primarily of bound manuscripts, many illustrated, from the 15th through the early 20th centuries. Most materials are in German or English, with some materials in French, Hebrew, Italian, Spanish, Swedish, Greek, or Latin. In addition to the above noted subgroups, the collection includes medical texts; historical chronicles, mostly German; and alchemical/astrological/occult treatises. Among the identified authors are Georg Fabricius, Edward Young, Sebastian Chiesa, Henry Marchant, Jacob Böhme, J.M. Firmenich, and Carl and Julius Dresel. For more information, please see the collection's finding aid.
There is also a collection of graphic arts featuring prints collected by Jantz from Europe, America, and Asia.
Contents of Collection
- Harold Jantz Papers, 1500-1982, (67 boxes)
  Professional correspondence, note cards, research and teaching files, essays, offprints and reprints of articles by Jantz and scholars associated with him, and other printed material. Notable items are manuscripts about Johann Wolfgang von Goethe and his Faust, and manuscripts related to Francis Daniel Pastorius's Bee-Hive (Box 32 of 1994-0001, Top of OC:IV).
  - Accession (1994-0001) (Box 1-33)
  - Accession (1996-0033) (Box 1-10)
  - Accession (1996-0097) (Box 1-20)
  - Accession (1998-0172) (Box 1-2)
  - Cards (Box 1-2)
- Accession (2008-0159), 1880-1985, (5 boxes)
  Accession (2008-0159) (2625 items; 3.5 lin. ft; dated 1880-1985) consists largely of Jantz's correspondence and letters, 1978-1985. Also included are exam blue books, some miscellaneous printed material, and a scrapbook of chromolithographs dating from the Victorian period. The blue books contain writings by Jantz, some relating to Francis Pastorius, and are arranged numerically. Most of the scrapbook's chromolithographs appear to be artwork promoting a particular brand or product.
  - Blue books (Box 1 (Acc. 08/159))
  - Correspondence, 1978-1985 (Box 2-4 (Acc. 08/159))
  - Scrapbook of chromolithographs, 1880-1910 (Box 5 (Acc. 08/159))
- Accession (2011-1043), 1950s-1980s, (6 boxes)
  Professional personal papers of Harold Jantz. Includes materials related to travel, his collecting, and academic correspondence. Also includes numerous drafts, notes (in exam blue books), and correspondence related to his research and writing about Goethe, Faust, German Americana, Baroque writings, and other topics.
  - Correspondence, 1970s-1980s (Box 1 (11/1043))
  - Correspondence (Box 2 (11/1043))
  - Writings, Notes, and Drafts
  - Writings, Notes, and Drafts (Box 3 (11/1043))
  - Writings, Notes, and Drafts (Box 4 (11/1043))
  - Correspondence
  - Research files and photocopies
  - Administrative and professional papers re: German Department, university work
  - Correspondence (Box 5 (11/1043))
  - Research files
  - Miscellaneous materials relating to Austrian apartments (Box 6 (11/1043))
  - Oversize items (Opaperfolder 1 (11/1043))